blogid;blogname;blogbody
1;PASS SQL Saturday #567 Slovenia 2016;The leading event dedicated to Microsoft SQL Server in Slovenia will take place on Saturday, 10th December 2016, at the Faculty of Computer and Information Science of the University of Ljubljana, Večna pot 113, Ljubljana (http://www.fri.uni-lj.si/en/about/how_to_reach_us/). As always, this is an English-only event. We don’t expect the speakers and the attendees to understand SlovenianSmile However, this way, our SQL Saturday has become quite well known especially in the neighboring countries. Therefore, expect not only international speakers, expect international attendees as well. There will be 30 top sessions, two original and interesting pre-conference seminars, a small party after the conference, an organized dinner for the speakers and sponsors… But first of all, expect a lot of good vibrations, mingling with friends, smiling faces, great atmosphere. You might also consider visiting Ljubljana and Slovenia for couple of additional days. Ljubljana is a very beautiful and lively city, especially in December.
2;Data Mining Algorithms – Neural Network;A neural network is a powerful data modeling tool that is able to capture and represent complex input/output relationships. The motivation for the development of neural network technology stemmed from the desire to develop an artificial system that could perform "intelligent" tasks similar to those performed by the human brain. The Neural Network algorithm is an artificial intelligence technique that explores more possible data relationships than other algorithms. Because it is such a thorough technique, the processing of it is usually slower than the processing of other classification algorithms. A neural network consists of basic units modeled after biological neurons. Each unit has many inputs that it combines into a single output value. These inputs are connected together, so the outputs of some units are used as inputs into other units. The network can have one or more middle layers called hidden layers. The simplest are feed-forward networks (pictured), where there is only a one-way flow through the network from the inputs to the outputs. There are no cycles in the feed-forward networks. As mentioned, units combine inputs into a single output value. This combination is called the unit’s activation function. An activation function has two parts. The first part is the combination function that merges all of the inputs into a single value (weighted sum, for example). The second part is the transfer function, which transfers the value of the combination function to the output value of the unit. The linear transfer function would do just the linear regression. The transfer functions are S-shaped, like the sigmoid function.
3;Data Mining Algorithms – Logistic Regression;It’s been awhile since I wrote the last blog on the data mining / machine learning algorithms. I described the Neural Network algorithm. In addition, it is a good time to write another post in order to remind the readers of the two upcoming seminars about the algorithms I have in Oslo, Friday, September 2nd, 2016, and in Cambridge, Thursday, September 8th. Hope to see you in one of the seminars. Finally, to conclude this marketing part: if you are interested in the R language, I am preparing another seminar “EmbRace R”, which will cover R from basics to advanced analytics. Stay tuned. Now for the algorithm. If you remember the post, a Neural network has an input, an output, and one or more hidden layers. The Neural Network algorithm uses the hyperbolic tangent activation function in the hidden layer and the sigmoid function in output layer. However, the Sigmoid function is called the Logistic function as well. Therefore, describing the Logistic Regression algorithm is simple after I described the Neural Network. If a neural network has only input neurons that are directly connected to the output neurons, it is a Logistic Regression. Or, to repeat the same thing in a different way: Logistic Regression is Neural Network with zero hidden layers. 
4;MDS 2016 Installation on Windows Server 2012 R2;This is a tip that should help installing SQL Server 2016 (tested on CTP33, RC2 and RC3) Master Data Services. The documentation is pretty old and incomplete (I already sent the feedback). The page “Web Application Requirements (Master Data Services)” (https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee633744.aspx) should be seriously updated. First of all, there should be documented also how to use operating systems Windows Server 2012 R2 and Windows 10. I managed to install it on Windows Server 2012 R2. However, there is a bullet missing in the Role and Role Services part. In the Performance section, only Static Content Compression is mentioned. However, Dynamic Content Compression is needed as well.
5;Truncate Table – DDL or DML Statement?;There is an ongoing discussion about this topic. However, if you quickly bingle for this question, you get the impression that the majority is somehow leaning more toward defining the TRUNCATE TABLE statement as a DDL statement. For example, Wikipedia clearly states: “In SQL, the TRUNCATE TABLE statement is a Data Definition Language (DDL) operation that marks the extents of a table for deallocation (empty for reuse).” Disclaimer: please note that I do not find Wikipedia as the “ultimate, trustworthy source” – I prefer sources that are signed! Some of the reasons why many people define the statement as a DDL statement include: It requests schema locks in some systems. It is not possible to rollback it in some systems. It does not include a WHERE clause. It does not fire triggers in some systems. It resets the autonumbering column value in some systems. It deallocates system pages directly, not through an internal table operation. On the other hand, it looks like there is only one reason to treat the statement as a DML statement: Logically, you just get rid of the data, like with the DELETE statement. Even the Wikipedia article that I referred to says “The TRUNCATE TABLE mytable statement is logically (though not physically) equivalent to the DELETE FROM mytable statement (without a WHERE clause).” Like many times, I have to disagree with the majority. I understand that the categorization is somehow confusing, and might even be overlapping. However, the only reason for categorizing the TRUNCATE TABLE statement in the DML category is “THE” reason in my understanding. One of the most important ideas in the Relational Model is the separation between the logical and the physical level. We, users, or people, if you wish, are manipulating with data on the logical level. The physical implementation is left to the database management system. And this is the important part – logically, when you truncate table, you don’t care how this statement is implemented internally, you just want to get rid of the data. It really does not matter what kind of locks a system uses, does it allow WHERE clause or not, etc. The logical point is what matters. Therefore, I would categorize the TRUNCATE TABLE statement as a DML statement.
